[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guest is Robert Secord Robert
Secord is the standardization lead at
woven by Toyota and is the convenient of
the C standards committee cord's
previous industry experience includes
roles at IBM and the X Consortium he was
a researcher carnegi melon University
software engineering Institute professor
at the carnegi melon School of computer
science and information networking
Institute what Mal and the University of
Pittsburgh his previous books include
the sear C coding standard effective C
which is now in its second edition and
the secure coding in C and C++
Robert welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything I missed in your
bio that you'd like to add no that
wasn't bad the most recent book was the
second edition of effective C published
recently by no starch press yeah it's a
good one I've got that I've gone through
a bit of it for this show so I'm excited
dig into bits with you cool for the
listeners the goals that we're trying to
achieve today is to have a short
refresher on C to understand what the C
standard specifically c23 brings
and to explore different sectors where
we might find these standards and see in
general so let's start I'd like to start
with a brief history of the sea language
what the C standard is and what the c c
coding standard is are you ready sure so
when was C created you should know this
instantly oh yeah cuz I was there I
think I was seven but it was developed
in the early 1970s at B Labs as a system
implementation Lang for Unix when it was
you know initially being developed there
at B labs and what is a standard what is
the c standard how do they relate yeah
so originally there was no C standard
there was what we call K andrc which was
named after the authors of the sea
language book back in the 70s kingham
and Richie and in the late' 70s folks
got together and decided ancy in
particular decided would be useful to
standardize the language the first
standard was created by ansy in 1989 and
that's referred to as c89 and then the
next year it was published by ISO as C90
and those two standards are identical
they just have different cover sheets
and there's continued to be standards
every decade or so since it's not a
quick process and the standard can kind
of be thought of you know it's sort of
an instructional manual for implementor
but is also a contract between compiler
implementers and users of the language
so the C language is defined by the
standard as opposed to you know a
particular implementation of that
standard and that's something you can
work on so say you've got the standard
in a PDF you can kind of work and know
that as long as you're compliant with it
things are going to work yeah it's
useful to have a copy the standard I
would say for the entire period of time
I was writing operational code in C I
did not own a copy of the
standard and so probably the biggest
disadvantage of not having standard is
knowing how to write portable code so
you know you can sort of experiment with
a given compiler and you know get your
code to work through trial and error and
testing but you don't really know if
that code is fully portable unless
you're familiar with the standard so
that's probably where the stand
provides the most benefit and you aware
of any other languages that are
standardized like this oh C++ is
standardized like this Ada Cobalt Fort
Tran these are all ISO languages there
are languages like Java and csharp where
the language itself defines the language
and if you have a sort of difference
between the C standard and the C
compiler the standard is considered to
be wrong so that's the opposite approach
from what C and other ISO languages take
before I mve us on to the c c coding
standard are you familiar with what it
takes for a language to be one you know
for there to be desire for it to be
standardized you know why isn't there a
Java standard or why isn't there a goang
standard or rust standard or something
yeah well you know Java was originally
developed by Sun Microsystems and sort
of controlled by Sun Microsystems so
they wanted to sort of keep control of
the language and the process so they
they did things like have Community
groups to provide them input but they're
still roughly under you know the control
of sun and then Oracle you know C was
implemented by different companies at
the same time and what was begin to
happen was there was a certain amount of
Divergence in the implementations so the
typical reason you standardize something
is to sort of limit the Divergence and
try to have a portable version of the
language that you could sort of easily
move between different platforms and
different compilers so you're saying the
standardization was done there because
of Divergence of the language yeah you
know different implementations were
going in different directions and there
was a desire to sort of try to maintain
the portability of code written in the C
language you know so that you could
easily Port it from one compiler
implementation to another and from one
platform to another with without too
much effort and does it make a big
difference on the compiler that you use
per well sure you know so to give an
example going into the C standardization
process with an and c89 there's this
concept called integer promotions in C
and you know roughly half the
implementations at that time had taken
approach called value preserving and the
other half took this approach of unsign
preserving so the committee eventually
agreed on using the value preserving
approach and then you know the roughly
half of the compilers who took the other
approach then had to change their
compilers and that also has a subsequent
impact on the users of the language rate
because now their compilers Chang their
version of the languages changed right
and so they have to now kind of retest
all their code and make sure it's still
correct given the changes required to
standardize and where was that example
from that was from late 1980s that makes
sense okay so the c c coding standard
yeah so C SE coding standard was
something I worked on at Carnegie Mill
University in the the C division of the
software engineering Institute that
actually came about I had started
working in the SE standards Committee in
2005 and about a year later I went to a
meeting in Berlin and Dr Thomas Plum
approached me Tom actually just recently
passed away which is sort of sad sorry
Taylor yeah he was a really great man so
he approached me with the idea of Sir
creating a secure coding standard and I
thought right away that's a great idea
and the concern at the time was the only
thing out there was from misra which is
more of a safety related standard and
they had their outs with the c committee
at the time and so I started the project
back at the SEI and we published a
couple books with Addison the first
edition was not very good so if you own
that I'm
sorry but it sort of got me a seat at
the table and we started a study group
in wg14 the C standards committee and we
met you know every couple weeks for
about 3 and a half years with Security
Experts and analyzers and compiler
vendors and we kind of ironed out a much
better version of the sear C standard so
we published that in two places one is
the second edition of the search C
coding standard with ason Wesley and we
also published it as a technical
specification with ISO called
17961 and the iso technical
specification was more targeted towards
sort of the analyzable subset of the
rules while the CC coding centers a
little more targeted towards developers
and what they needed to do to ensure the
security of their systems even say in
cases where the enforcement of those
rules was not easily tool
analyzable so if you took program in C
to the C standard your program might not
be secure oh yeah it's pretty easy to
write an insecure program in C it's
really pretty easy to write an insecure
program in any language there's a lot of
things people aren't aware of until they
sort of develop a bit of a security
mindset and the start of that is that
the user is really actually out to get
you in many cases so when you take an
untrusted input from a user you know
Sloss attacker you have to be very
careful with those inputs you have to
make sure you validate them you have to
be very careful how you use them or they
might result in some sort of exploit and
that's true of really all languages all
programming languages so why is C still
so popular if it was created when you
are seven years old well you know it's
been doing the job you know I mean the
kind of advantage of see
that makes it attractive is that it's a
small relatively simple language it's
very fast and it just does what you tell
it to do it doesn't do anything else and
so frequently people need that level of
control over their programs because they
might have to run fast they might have
to be close to the hardware so you know
see fits you know a niche that is still
sort of important today maybe that's
like you know in software engineering
every 20 years we kind of reinvent
things with a new generation so maybe
with the evolving landscape of language
is getting taught at universities and
startups and things it's just not
getting so many new projects I mean
should someone start a new projecting C
today or is C just there to be
maintained you know what's your view on
that yeah I mean I'm going to give an
answer that sounds like a non-answer but
you should start a new project and see
if C is the right language for that
project and so there are areas where C
is quite well I'll say is sort of best
suited still right so for example if
you're developing safety related systems
it's still a little premature to build
those systems in Rust because the
ecosystem around rust is not fully
developed yet so you don't really have
the rust standards that are required for
certification you don't have the
certified libraries and a lot of the
components that you need need to build
uh safety critical software so you know
if you have a team of developers and
they're C language experts and you have
to develop you know a safety related
system then C is your best choice you
know you you can't underestimate skill
sets and things like that with the
developers you have you know if you took
a bunch of expert C programmers and you
asked them to build a system in Rust
chances are good that system won't be as
good as the C system would have been
just because of the famili famity with
The Language by the developers so are we
saying if I understand that right pick
the right tool for the right job yeah
that's a good summary and the niche
might be safety related systems and
what's the definition of safety related
systems is that medical Aviation yeah
medical Aviation are both good examples
I work in automotive so Automotive is a
good example so yeah there's still a
variety of safety related domains in
which C and C+ plus are the safe choice
right and rust would be considered you
know a really sort of risky bold choice
to make it this time and eventually rust
will get there right but it's not
necessarily there quite yet yeah that
surprised me because normally you'd
think with a safety standard and all the
things you hear about the exploits and C
that it wouldn't be used in a safe
environment but because you've got the
libraries that are certified and things
to reference to create and sign the off
in medical I completely understand what
you're saying about the immaturity of
some ecosystems right and rust you know
has some advantages over CN C++ it's
designed to be sort of a memory safe
language you know the joke is that you
know programming is hard and you know
rust enforces that at compile time maybe
the joke was programming is impossible
and rust enforces that at compile time
that would have been funnier so yes
their advantages of R there but many of
the common sort of vulnerabilities are
still quite possible so you know no
language that I'm aware of enforces
input validation right that's always
left to the programmer and so you know
all languages there are no secure
languages right they're all susceptible
to exploits in one sense or another yeah
I suppose there a trade-off between
developing a safety related piece of
software and the time that takes to do
it extra versus some of the quick wins
you get in the other languages you know
that aren't certified but give you a lot
more art of the Starting Gate as it were
right yeah I mean c is not a scripting
language right so you would probably be
more likely to use python or something
like that it's not a web development
language you know you would be more
likely to use JavaScript or typescript
or something like that so you know
languages all have kind of their sweet
spot and you know that's still true of C
today there's still various applications
you know which are really best suited
for C and of course there's the however
many you know 50 Years of Legacy code
out there which basically is what the
world runs on is old C code yeah exactly
and is there if somebody asks you where
I shouldn't you see is there something
for that or is there never a wrong place
to you see if you know what you're doing
yeah there is I mean I've I've never
seen well I I guess never is a strong
word right it's pretty unusual to see
cuse for a browser web browser
application right that's pretty uncommon
and I wouldn't recommend it and you know
it's probably not the best language for
scripting type programs things that you
have to kind of get up and run quickly
so you know different languages again
have their roles and there are
applications that are not well suited to
see well thank you we're going to move
us on to our next section which is
everything you and see given it so we're
always adding new things with the
standards so the latest standard I
didn't clarify before but you called it
c89 Sor I presume that's 1989 and now
c23 which is the latest standard is
obviously
2023 right we have our own Y2K problem
with the naming of the standards so once
we get up to
2089 there's going to be some ambiguity
in the names and you know given how long
cobal has been around I wouldn't be
surprised if if we do get there
eventually one of my grandchildren may
be running the C committee by then it'll
definitely still be around because I'm
not going to rewrite some of the things
that are written in C are they right so
now that we've had a good refresher on C
bearing in mind that we last spoke in
2020 four years already what does c23
give us or in fact as we're discussing
c23 if there's something that you want
our listeners to be highlighted on
that's new from c21 so the standard from
2021 if you have any time feel free to
mention that oh well there is no c21 so
the current version of the C standard is
c17 so that's the last published version
c23 we finished work on that in 2023 and
it's almost
published so I I think we have a
commitment from ISO to complete the
editing process by December of this year
but it's been a long road with I so this
has kind of been sort of an ISO issue
because it's not just our committees
other committees that are sort of being
affected by these long editing schedules
and that's the is international standard
organization isn't it right over there
in Geneva yeah so attributes you were
looking at them in C11 but they didn't
get standardized then yeah we ended up
adding some keyword sort of specified
attributes C++ on the other and did wind
up adopting a standard attribute syntax
but we did get around to them finally in
c23 and you know it's a useful feature
it's kind of you know it's new so people
keep coming up with new things to do
with it right because it's got that
shiny new car smell I think you've
mentioned cars everyone listen to this
podcast in a car or walk or run are
going to be going what is an attribute
so if you want to Define it for us that'
be cool yeah so an attribute is a way to
give sort of information to the compiler
in a way that if the attribute isn't
support it it's not going to affect the
outcome of the program right so a lot of
times they're just sort of hints to the
compiler that it can used for
optimization things like this so
examples of C attributes which are also
present in C++ include maybe unused no
discard you know meaning that you
shouldn't discard a value return from a
function and if you do the compiler
should issue a diagnostic again it
changes the behavior of the compiler but
doesn't affect the type of code that's
generated there's a deprecated attribute
kind of have a similar effect there's a
no return attribute that you can use to
indicate say for example that the
function calls a boort along all
possible control flows so there's no
possible way for that function to return
and as a consequence the compiler can
now sort of make optimizations based on
that information so is this syntax above
a function signature or something like
that it changes a little bit depending
on what it applies to so the syntactic
location of the attribute determines you
know what it's applying to so it might
apply to you know the function or it
might apply to a function parameter sort
of depending on where it's positioned so
you need to look at some examples or
look at the grammar in the standard to
make sure that you're placing the
attributes correctly perfect so the next
item I have on my list is keywords oh
yeah keywords so C does something a
little bit different than C++ which is
we have a reserved name space of
identifiers that we expect the users not
to use and so we're pretty comfortable
just CL ing those right we'll just take
it over for our own use because we
reserve them and the problem is that if
a user if a programmer has used that
identifier right now you've got multiple
definitions and and that could cause
problems so we also sometimes want to
use a keyword that's not in the reserve
space and good examples of that are when
we added the Bull type when we added
static assertions the static assert
macro a line of and things like that so
what C does to try to not break user
code is a process called
uglification and we really do call it
that so for example buou most developers
would expect that to be spelled b o l
sort of like int is spelled boou but we
put it underbar and then we capitalized
the first letter so it was in c17 it's
spelled underbar capital B lowercase ool
so it's a sort of very ugly version and
that also the underbar followed by
capital letter is in the reserved
identifier space so if you've used that
we don't feel bad about clobbering it
because we'd reserved it so we had all
these kind of ugly keyword spellings in
c17 and as part of c23 we replace those
with sort of the modern spelling so now
buou is b o l and static assert is
static assert and so now you can just
use those keywords without having to
include any particular headers and you
know again you know we try to be very
careful with c not to break existing
code because you know as I pointed out
earlier the world runs on C and no one
on the committee wants to be responsible
for breaking the world so we try to be
quite careful with these things and that
was Yen as a good stad yeah yan yan
gooded I believe wrote that paper yeah
that we I spoke to him I think six
months or a year before I spoke to you
in 2020 yeah I think I saw him on your
channel yeah he he's a very strong
contributor to see standards that's
brilliant okay so the next one integer
constant expression sounds exciting what
was that I'm glad you can be excited by
integer constant expression not I'm
hoping it spills over not many people
can but yeah so in c23 we added con
exper which is familiar to C++
developers we added it only for object
definitions and not yet for function def
definitions which you know fans of con
expert are immediately disappointed by
that that we didn't go further but part
of the problem with in constant
Expressions is that they not a portable
construct so vendors are allowed to
extend it so you could declare a
function with say a const int and then
use that object to provide the size of
an array and on some implementations
that array might be statically sized
array and on other implementations it
might be a variable length of a vaa so
this is a good application for these new
constant expert objects where if you
declare your size as a const expert
object now you're portably guaranteed to
not have a variable length array so it
improves the portability of your code
yeah because on some platforms integers
could be treated differently yeah even
constant so constant might be a constant
expression on one implementation but not
a constant expression in another
inflation which is confusing and hence
that's sort of where the problem lies
there's no point thinking of every
scenario until it comes across and then
you need to deal with it right so the
next one another exciting one for me
enumeration types yeah I I like this
change so most of this change was just
the ability to have typed enumerations
where the developer explicitly says what
type it is so prior to this change you
sort of had to guess so so it really
could be any any type up to int or
unsigned in and some common
implementations I believe for example
Microsoft Visual C used a signed int and
GCC used an unsigned int right so you
got different behaviors on different
platforms and that could of course
affect portability and how you write
your code and so now you know with c23
you can give a type so you can specify
this enum is unsigned short this enum is
an unsigned int and you know now you've
dot uh more portable Behavior because
you know exactly what type is being used
to represent the underlying enumeration
object if you want to use these things
now I mean we've only gone through half
of the list is it just a case of using a
compiler that sorts supports or do you
need to do something else well you need
a compiler that supports these c23
features and you need to change your
code so you would have to go through
your source code and add the type
specific ification to each enum that
you've defined and the binary that's
produced is just a binary as how that's
always produced yeah it'll compile down
to a binary and you know the binary
could well be different right if you've
specified a type for that enum that's
different from what the default type
would have been under you know c17 or
old diversions the other thing to be you
know concerned about is you know before
you sort of modernize your source code
to c23 you want to make sure that those
c23 features are available on all the
possible you know platforms that you're
targeting right because otherwise you
you wind up doing more work with you
know having defines and things like that
and different sort of configurations of
your program depending on your your
target compiler yeah and you end up
writing three times the amount of code
just to do the one thing depending on
where it's deployed exactly but it is a
good feature and it does improve
portability improves Safety and Security
because it makes your program better
defined and it's always good to you know
know what your code is actually doing
right yeah make it easier to read as
well because you've explicitly said what
it is right so next one is type and
inference yeah type inference is sort of
surprising to me that this became one of
the more controversial new features in C
there are a lot of people who really
don't want C to change at all and a few
of them are on the committee so this is
you know use of Auto and and it's the
same idea as in in C++ but we don't
allow it in function signatures and so
what you can do is you can say you know
Auto you know I equals 0 L and the
compiler will infer the type of the
object based on how you initialize it so
in this case if we initialize it to Zer
L the L is the long constant right so it
will declare this type as a long so it's
sort of a convenient feature it is sort
of susceptible to abuse which is why
maybe some folks are not super fond of
it but it's useful in sort of macro
definitions function like macros where
you don't know what the type of the
parameters are but you want to declare
an object of that type you could simply
use Auto there and it's also useful in
so generic programming which in case you
haven't used a new vers of C in a long
time we've had for a while now in the
language yeah I was going to ask it cuz
that sounds like in Pearl or python you
know depending on whether the variable
looks like a string or looks like a
number or looks like an array the
variable behind the scenes will change
right right I just trying to understand
what the reason for that was yeah mostly
to support you know generic programming
if I had to give a on line answer and
what's the short definition of generic
programming for those not familiar
including myself so two sort of generic
features so there's the old school
generic feature which are you know
function like macros right where say you
define a swap function you know a swap
macro and you know most experien C
programs will know that the actual
arguments that you pass to macro can be
any type at all because it's just going
to be sort of textual replacement and as
long as the resulting code makes sense
it will compile and things will be fine
so that's sort of the old school way of
doing it but in C11 we introduce generic
selection uh statement where now you can
actually sort of branch on the type of
the parameters and invoke different code
and that code will now be type checked
and all those good things that come with
not using macros nice and macros is the
syntax you use in pre-processing isn't
it pre-processing right pre-processing
macros so the pound sign define
basically perfect type of operators
that's one word type of type of yeah
there's type of and type of unal these
are similar to The Deco type in C++ so
it's another way to let you specify a
type in your code based on another type
or the type of an expression and so the
difference between those two operators
and these These are both operators is
that type of retains whatever qualifiers
the origal type have like volatile or
const or Atomic and type of unal strips
the qualifiers including any Atomic
qualifier and that might be where you're
trying to to find available to live in
one source code file or one program
right it's another useful feature for
macros or for generic functions perfect
and second last is bit and bite
utilities yeah this was done by John
heed minid so there's a new header
called uh standard bit. and there's just
a ton of new functions you know so we
have functions that let you count the
number of ones or zeros in a bit pattern
count the number of leading or trailing
ones or zeros test whether a bit is set
determine the smallest number of bits
required to represent the value just a
bunch of different you know bit
twiddling type of functions that are now
uh standardized and we also have a
feature test macro standard C Indian
native that lets you determine whether
your integers are represented using
either big or or little Indian
representation this area of c and
probably software engineer in general
I've not done a lot of personally any
sort of bite operations at all what
where is that used primarily in sort of
lowlevel programming there's a book I'm
forgetting the name I think it was
called hacks or something like that
really very clever book but it talked
about how you can write really efficient
code with a variety of sort of these bit
level hacks so these sort of functions
make that easier but also just for this
very kind of lowlevel code where you're
dealing with Hardware masks and those
type of things yeah the first thing that
comes to my mind is where you're doing
embedded programming and you're sending
a one or zero to light up an LED or
something you know different that I just
had this thought for the first time
which is always scary to then you know
record that on a radio show but this
idea that you can that there's a
function to determine the smallest
number of bits required to represent a
value that could be quite useful with
the new bit precise integer types we
have in c23 where you can specify the
exact size the exact number of bits
that's going to be used to represent
that type that's a good idea so we're on
to our last one now and I'll need to get
that linked to that book afterwards so
we can put in the show
notes so our last one is the i e floa
Point support so we have a c floating
Point study group and and thank God we
have them because they handle all this
floating Point stuff that you know
befuddles the the rest of the committee
but the big change in
c23 is that there are a number of
technical specifications
18661 D one-2 and-3 and those have all
been now folded into
c23 and so the part one of those
technical specifications deals with
binary floating point the part two deals
with decimal floating point and the part
three deals with interchange and so
those changes are very extensive and
have introduced all sorts of new
identifiers and it's very complete it
also sort of you know updates C to work
with itle e 754 2008 version of the
floating point stand standard so that's
good you kind of do this thing in
standards world where you Leap Frog each
other right when we come out with a new
standard we see what other standards
have have published new editions since
the last time we published and we try to
update our standards to work with the
latest greatest things how many hours of
your life do you have to commit this to
know and read off those numbers by heart
like you just did the standards oh you
know listing them off is pretty easy
like understanding floating point that
takes your entire life I mean there's a
really very small number of people who
completely understand floating point and
how do you describe it well floating
point is a model that approximately
models the behavior of real numbers but
doesn't really it's not the same as
performing arithmetic with real numbers
but it comes close to it right and so
that's always good and bad right so
people will use it to Implement
arithmetic using real numbers and
normally it works and then sometimes it
doesn't right and where and how it
doesn't behave the same is why you need
to be an expert in floating point when
you use floating Point floating point is
at like 10.2 53 2 1 is that a floating
Point number or any real number right so
even like say 0.1 or 1.0 you know can be
a floating Point number right if it's in
a floating Point type such as float or
double and you know if I just use 0.1 as
an example right when you look at that
number in binary floating point you
think that's a really simple number
right but it turns out in binary
floating point that number cannot be
exactly represented and so there's a c
yeah but it's it's 0.1 that's what it is
that's what you think it is but when you
represent it as a floating Point number
it's not exactly that number it's
something close to that number and so
there's a certain lack of in ision there
which can kind of wind up biting you
it's a weird story to tell it's a real
world example except it turns out it was
it's not true it was different but it's
a good story anyway but back in the
1990s you know when we had the Desert
Storm the US you know invasion of Iraq
there was a scud missile launch on on
some barracks in in Saudi Arabia and the
barracks were be defended by the this
Patriot batteries and it turned out the
Patriot batteries had failed to
intercept one of these scud missiles
which hit the barracks and caused some
deaths among the US troops there and so
this problem this this defect was
originally attributed to floating Point
representation and that because these
batteries had been continually
operational for a long period of time as
it ran the floating Point values became
increasingly imprecise to the point that
event eventually the missiles failed to
intercept the you know the scud missiles
coming in the reality of it is very
close to that the reality of is that it
was actually imprecision in these
floating Point numbers but it then
caused the conversion to an integer to
to be incorrect and so you know the
solution to that was to turn the
batteries off and on every you know
every so often so so these imprecisions
didn't accumulate and then you know
eventually there was a uh there was a
soft for fixed to solve the problem it
sounds like the age-old It fix just
reboot it yeah just turn it off and turn
it on again yeah okay that's the last
one in c23 but did we have we missed
anything you know you probably
missed my favorite and maybe many's
people's favorite which is starting with
c23 the c language only supports TW
complement integer representations so
you know as of c17 the C language
support two's compliment one's
complement and sign and magnitude and
this is one of these changes you know
that I didn't think I would live to see
yeah it's a backward step is that not I
don't think so because like sign and
magnitude representation that's very
very outdated one's complement is one
that we thought was kind of still around
but you know we determined that really
it's not it doesn't exist in any current
implementations and so when you you can
narrow what's Allowed by the standard
that that's really the purpose of
standardization right now the standard
provides more portability guarantees
right so all you as a developer have to
do is write code that will work with a
tw's compliment representation and that
code will Now function correctly on any
c23 conforming compiler yeah that's a
big win yeah I think so perfect yeah so
we did that and yeah some other things
but too numerous to talk about here well
the last question of this section was to
talk about anything in c21 that is a
must have but c21 as it doesn't exist
doesn't exist believe that question
that's a new one for me okay so as we
said in the intro you work for woven by
Toyota so I wondering if we could talk
about that your work there how C fits in
you know obviously don't talk about
things you can't talk about but what is
woven and what's their goal you know as
a elevator pitch yeah so woven is in the
Toyota group of companies so my my
office is actually in Tokyo although I
work remotely from my my home in
Pittsburgh you know woven is basically
trying to Define what we call the
softwar defined vehicle and you know so
historically cars have been sort of a
collection built from a collection of
components which are sort developed by
sort of a diverse ecosystem of vendors
and then you know integrated by the OEM
which might be Toyota Ford or or
Mercedes or what have you and you know
the software is developed for each
component and then basically discard it
and then you know for the next version
of the vehicle or or a different vehicle
then you know a new set of components
are developed and that's sort of a
increasingly unviable way to build cars
which are increasingly software Reliant
and so we're trying to sort of flip the
script on that and you know sort of
Define the vehicle in terms of the
software and then provide the hardware
that can then you know run that software
in a safe reliable way so that's very
interesting about woven so they're
designing just to summarize they're
designing the software first so it kind
of grows with the vehicle rather than
develop software for a component then
the new version of that vehicle has to
get the same process done again and
again right so this is the goal
basically to be able to sort of preserve
the software evolve it over time and
have sort of increasingly you know
complex systems that have sort of like
reusable software kind of following the
concept of product lines if you're
familiar with that okay are they working
with other manufacturers to create some
type of standard around this as well or
is that too early yeah it's probably too
early I mean right now this concept is
competing with with sort of the current
model right where you know existing
vendors sort of entrenched in the the
current approach and you know we sort of
have to still sort of move the industry
in this direction right so it's it's a
goal it's our goal but it's by no means
accomplished the goal yet understood and
where does c fit into all this well C
and C++ are probably the primary
languages in which we you know develop
Automotive software just because you
know there is this established ecosystem
around these languages and companies
like Toyota are are very comfortable
building or developing Automotive
software in those languages in C and C++
is C kind of powers the operating system
or is that C++ or C just speaks to the
individual OEM part I've always wanted
to know how the systems in a car are
linked and hopefully you are privy to
that type of thing yeah to a degree they
don't really let me write any software
anymore so I I'm mostly involved in the
the coding standards and so forth but
you know on an embedded processor you
don't really have an operating system
right you're just kind of on the metal
but there are things like Automotive
grade Linux which might be on a car and
in that case you know the operating
system is written in in C because a line
is Carval can't stand C++ so it's
you won't have it you know in Linux in
terms of how the systems you know there
can be up to say 100 ecus in a in a
modern vehicle so the vehicle internally
has something called a can bus and
that's how the ecus communicate and the
more modern vehicles have sort of more
complex networks which I'm not not
exactly sure what those look like but
you know there'll be sort of subnets
which are Gateway off of other other
networks so potentially you're cyber
physical safety components ecus will be
you know
gatewayedi ecus for example so you're
involved in the standards around all the
C code that is used in these safety
related systems you know really all of
it so okay the first coding standards I
wrote for woven were for C++ for C++ 14
and C++ 17 and I'm just actually now
completing a CST standard around the c17
version of the standard and these are
you know coding standards which
integrate safety related coding
standards such as misra and autosar and
also integrate the search standards
which thankfully Toyota had already
adopted the search standards before I
began working there so I didn't have to
sort of do this in modest thing of
promoting my own you know Creations so
that was that was nice and these
standards they could coding standards
that the developers Follow by reading it
or are they helped with the compilers or
the idees or how does it enforce so for
these Mis based standards and autosar
based standards we have something called
a guideline enforcement plan which goes
through each of the rules and talks
about how it's enforced and normally
it's enforced by some sort of static
analysis tool and so examples of those
include code ql or parasoft C++ plus
test or qac Helix I think it's called
that's those are some examples ldra also
has a conformance analysis tool and so
you know we go through each rule and we
point at which Checker can you know
check conforms with that rule and then
in some cases some of the rules which
aren't automatable are enforced through
code reviews and other quality assurance
processes so these are done not at
compile time but through a separate tool
the stuff analysis is that correct right
yeah so so static analysis is run
separately typically after you know you
can successfully compile the code and
the reason for that is that some of this
analysis can take quite a bit of time
and the compilers are really focused on
sort of quick turnover right because
people have a lot of you know edit
compile test Cycles right and they don't
want to wait very long for their
compilations to complete so yeah it is
typical ult to sort of break those out
into separate tools and this is would be
the trade-off that for example Russ made
where they try and do as much as they
can up front in the compile bit versus
but that's not safety though it's not
safety related but yeah I'd say that's
true I mean Russ tries to prevent you
from you know getting any sort of
incorrect code to compile and the C
ecosystem is not necessarily less
but it requires that you have a little
bit more discipline in that once you get
your code to compile say your code
compiles it has a bunch of warnings
right it still generates an executable
and if you're a really bad programmer
you might decide to deploy that right
onto a system that's poor practice right
so first of all compiler warnings are
important you know you should address
all the warnings first and then you want
to do additional analysis both static
analysis Dynamic analysis you know
testing to make sure that you've
eliminated other categories of errors
that you know you don't want to deploy
to your your system yeah exactly just a
question that's popped out of that last
conversation do you have you seen or is
there or do you ever envisioned a way
that you could plug in these standards
at compile time to see or for example
rust instead of just enforcing what the
language do you can enforce course other
rules that are safety specific or will
it always be static and ask that
ecosystem is very mature I mean there's
probably no inherent reason why you
can't do it you know you could quite
possibly you know cang has the cang an
analyzer which is a stack and as to
right I could Envision you know Kang
introducing a flag that you know
compiler flag this says also invoked the
analyzer you know it's not really
necessary right I mean it makes more
sense to my mind right that you do the
compilation and at this point you're
trying to fix warnings you're trying to
get kind of obvious you know syntax
errors this kind of thing so you don't
want to do spend the time waiting for a
complete analysis to finish you just
want you know to kind of fix these
problems quickly and then once you get
to the point where you know it's free
from warnings and you know it's sort of
passing some unit tests maybe before the
unit test I don't know then then you can
do the static analysis and you can look
for additional harder to find problems
yeah it might slow down productivity
because the warnings are so not related
to what you're working on but you know
you're going to fix them at some point
right right yeah obviously C is still
and always will be a very powerful
language has a strong history in
deployment base and if there was one
thing that you'd like our listeners
software Engineers to remember from the
show what would you like it to be Robert
you know C is a strong and flexible
language it's sort of a Sharp tool and
you can get a lot done with it it but
you need to be informed and you know
have a good understanding of the
language and you know program safely
perfect and finally is there anything
that we missed that you think we should
have mentioned yeah run out and get a
copy of effective SE second edition of
course how could I forget effective SE
second edition it makes a great
Christmas present for I'm looking at my
one on the shelf and it's not too thick
but it's packed with so much information
well thank you very much appreciate it
okay so people can follow you on X I
suppose now Twitter old school I'm still
on Twitter for the time being and over
there on mastedon and Linkedin and I'm
not too hard to find people regularly
shoot me emails or you know complain
about the SE language on Twitter and I
I'll engage sometimes and if there's an
acon acronym that I've forgot to write
down or put in the show notes and they
want to reach out any of those in
particular that you're more fond of or
hang around more or does it matter I
sort of look at them all so however
you'd like best you know whatever system
you're on whatever social media you're
on that you'd like to contact me that's
fine okay Robert thank you for coming on
the show it's been a real pleasure and
this is Gavin Henry for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio and educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening